Guide to the Lewis Perry Curtis Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Lewis and Mary Elizabeth (Beers) Curtis had four children who lived to adulthood. Three were sons. Joseph Davis Beers Curtis became a partner in L. & B. Curtis & Co. Benjamin L. Curtis also followed a business career, but third son Lewis Agur Curtis after dabbling in the importing business devoted his life to travel and literature. Lewis Agur Curtis, the grandfather of Lewis Perry Curtis, married Emma Sophia Steele in 1859. The Steele and Perry letters in the collection mostly come from this alliance, although two of the sisters of Joseph D. Beers married Perrys. (Please examine the family charts for additional information on these family connections). Lewis Agur Curtis had two sons, Roderick Perry, the father of Lewis Perry Curtis, and Lewis Beers Curtis. Both followed business careers. In 1882 Roderick entered into partnership with William D. Forbes to form Forbes & Curtis, a manufacturer of machine tools in Bridgeport, Connecticut. After Forbes withdrew from business in 1887, Roderick was joined by his brother and the firm became known as Curtis & Curtis. Roderick died in 1909 leaving his wife and children in comfortable circumstances, but his brother Lewis Beers Curtis continued to manage Curtis & Curtis. He was also president of Beers Realty Co., which held many of the assets of Joseph D. Beers and Lewis Curtis, and the People's Savings Bank of Bridgeport. At his death in 1938 Lewis Beers Curtis left an estate of more than $6,000,000.
The correspondence, arranged chronologically, contains information on three major subjects; family activities, religion, and business. There is a great deal of news of family and friends, focusing on their daily activities, travel, education, health, etc. News of the doings of the Perrys, Steeles, and Marvines in the Auburn, Delaware County, New York area is recounted in letters written mostly by Julia (Perry) Steele, Augusta (Perry) Steele, and Roderick C. Steele. Julia Sophia (Perry) Steele, who died of consumption in February, 1832 at the age of twenty-three, gives news of family, discusses her health, and writes of her devotion to God in letters to her sister-in-law in Woodbury, Connecticut between 1829 and 1831 and in an 1831 diary (Box 34, folder 944).
When Joseph D. and Mary (Chapman) Beers made a trip to the South in 1834 and 1835, they recounted their travels in a series of letters to Lewis and Mary Elizabeth (Beers) Curtis. Joseph Davis Beers Curtis went to Paris in 1847 to head the Paris office of L. & B. Curtis & Co., succeeding his Uncle Benjamin.
Benjamin L. Curtis also spent several years abroad, attending school in Crefeld, France and touring Europe after graduation from Columbia in 1855. After the death of his wife in 1893, Lewis Agur Curtis devoted much of his last years to travel. The section contains letters he wrote from Europe in 1894, the west coast in 1898, the Near East in 1902, and the West Indies in 1903.
The most interesting letters from abroad were those written by Joseph D. B. Curtis from Paris between 1847 and 1867. His last letter was written in January 1867 shortly before he suffered a mental break-down, brought on, perhaps, by his own poor business judgement. Joseph was committed to an insane asylum in April 1867 suffering from "progressive paralysis" and "derangement of Mind," He died there three years later leaving behind the ruins of L. & B. Curtis & Co. Joseph's Paris letters are filled with the details of American society in Paris and are useful for information they give on his efforts to establish an American church in Paris, his heavy personal expenses, and his business failures. As he stated desparingly in a letter to his father in December 1860, "I confess that the more I think, the darker the future seems to me…. I am 36 years old, have labored faithfully to support myself and family for 15 years, came to Paris with nearly $30,000, and today all is gone, and I am $20,000 worse than nothing.
Religion is the second major subject discussed in the correspondence. Many of the correspondents were the products of the Great Revival of the 1820s and 1830s. Lewis Curtis, as mentioned above, was active in benevolent causes and his wife was extremely devout. Young Julia Steele found strength in her religious convictions when she was fighting a fatal disease. Joseph D. B. Curtis was also extremely religious, although it is conceivable that his piety was partly caused by the spectre of financial ruin. In a letter to his father in June 1858, after the death of grandmother Curtis, he expounded at length on death and the truths of the Bible. Edward Livingston Wells, grandfather of Lewis Perry Curtis, was an Episcopal priest, but the collection contains little to document his career.
Family business activities are also discussed in considerable detail in Personal Papers. Letters to and from several Beers and Curtises discussing business matters have been placed in this section of Series IV because they often contain personal news as well. The greatest volume of correspondence relating to business affairs concerns the problems of Joseph D. B. Curtis and L. & B. Curtis & Co. See Business Papers for more information on this subject.
The great majority of letters are written by relatives listed in the genealogical charts, but the section also contains letters beginning in 1855 from Louis Delafield, Oscar Smedberg, and Herbert B. Turner, Columbia classmates of Benjamin L. Curtis. Mary (Chapman) Beers corresponded during the 1830s with Mrs. Amelia Wainwright of Boston and Mary E. Edmonston of Charlestown, South Carolina. Also included are letters from Helen W. Turell, niece of the third wife of Joseph D. Beers, to Benjamin L. Curtis between 1885 and 1896, letters from Addy Pingree to Augusta (Perry) Steele in the early 1890s, and a series of more than fifty letters from architect George Martin Huss (1853-1941) to Roderick P. Curtis from 1891 to 1893. Huss designed the Curtis home in Southport, Connecticut.
Boxes 30-34 contain a wide variety of family papers, including deeds, memoranda, wills, estate papers, receipts, letter books, contracts, and speeches. These personal files are arranged alphabetically by name of family member and then chronologically within folders. The files are especially useful for biographical information. A day book kept by Benjamin L. Curtis in 1893, for example, contains notes in European history plus clippings and snippets of biographical information. A Lewis Curtis letter book covering the 1860-1867 period contains additional material on the difficulties of Joseph D. B. Curtis in Paris.
The Business Papers section of Series IV fills boxes 35-45. It contains correspondence, subject files, one box of oversized materials, and four boxes of bound business records. Business Papers primarily chronicles the careers of two nineteenth century New York City entrepreneurs, Joseph D. Beers and Lewis Curtis, although there is also a great deal of information on the business dealings of Benjamin, Joseph D. B., and Benjamin L. Curtis. Business correspondence, folders 966-985, covers the years 1801-1902 and is arranged in chronological order. The greatest volume of correspondence concerns the settlement of the estate of Andrew Beers, the collapse of L. & B. Curtis & Co., and speculation in oil lands. Alanson. Hamlin (1778-1839) of Danbury, Connecticut, administrator of the estate of Andrew Beers, wrote a series of letters to Joseph D. Beers between 1824 and 1828 on the division of property among Beers heirs. Material on L. & B. Curtis & Co. is found in this part of Business Papers, but also in Personal Papers, and the subject file L. & B. Curtis & Co., Boxes 38-39, folders 1042-1050, and folder 1100 of Box 41. William H. Ashton wrote several letters to Benjamin L. Curtis between 1895 and 1898 urging him to invest in land in Missouri and elsewhere that might contain oil. Business correspondence also contains a variety of letters on other matters. August Belmont (1816-1890) in an 1839 letter to Joseph D. Beers, for example, gives a statement of Beers' account with N. M. Rothschild & Sons of London. In a letter dated Paris October 17, 1859, American inventor W. H. Ward of Auburn, New York, asks Joseph D. B. Curtis for financial assistance in patenting and promoting four railroad inventions in France. Also included is an 1861 letter from Cyrus W. Field (1819-1892) concerning the Atlantic cable.
The bulk. of the material in Business Papers, however, is in alphabetically arranged subject files, Boxes 35-40. In addition to financial statements, announcements, agreements, memoranda, deeds, bills, and receipts, some subject files contain correspondence. Letters directly concerning a specific subject can be found in the following files: Apalachicola Land Co.; Booaem & Co. (Texas lands); Chetwood, F.B.; Farmers Loan & Trust Co.; 50th and 51st Street lands; Moffat & co.; New York and Mississippi Land Co.; and Sherwood, Samuel and Michigan lands.
For the entrepreneurial activities of Joseph D. Beers see the subject files for American Land Co, Apalachicola Land Co., Arkansas lands, Chetwood, F.B., 50th and 51st Street lands, Moffat & Co, New York and Mississippi Land Co, Pennsylvania lands, Sherwood, Samuel and Michigan lands and Thomas Wilson & Co. Business activites for Lewis Curtis are found in Booraem & Co. (Texas lands), Chichester lands, Curtis & Lamb, Eldert lands, Farmers Loan & Trust Co., Flatbush lands, Florida Peninsula Land Co., Indian Reservation Trust lands, Indiana and Illinois lands, Jones & Curtis, L. & B. Curtis & Co, Louisville and Portland Land Co, Mississippi Union Bank, and New York and Mississippi Land Co.
The files for Booraem & Co. (Texas lands) are contained in folders 984-1007 and 1085. The partnership of Booraem and Co. was established in 1834, and, although the company was reorganized at least twice, it collapsed in 1840. One of the partners, Henry Augustus Booaem (-1889) later became a partner in L. & B. Curtis & Co. Booraem & Co. was primarily engaged in the "business of jobbing Dry goods," but one of the partners purchased 2200 acres in the Republic of Texas. Lewis and Benjamin Curtis were among the creditors of Booraem & Co. and Lewis Curtis became its trustee. The problem of the title to the Texas lands, however, was not settled until the successful prosecution of a legal case in 1893. The files contain a substantial group of letters from Galveston, Texas land agent H.M. Truehart and the Galveston law firm of Davidson & Minor in regard to title to the land.
The Chetwood, F.B. materials, Box 37, folders 1008-1014, are also interesting. Francis B. Chetwood married a sister of the second wife of Joseph D. Beers and the correspondence concerns railroad construction and railroad politics in New Jersey between 1859 and 1862.
The history of L. & B. Curtis & Co. is also documented in considerable detail, folders 1042-1050 and 1100. The company was established in 1843. The original partners were Lewis Curtis, Benjamin Curtis, Henry A. Booraem, and John L. Hubbard. Joseph D. B. Curtis and Bernard Probst joined the firm at a later time. The direct antecedent of L. & B. Curtis & Co. was the partnership of Lewis & Benjamin Curtis, a French dry good importing business established in 1827. L. & B. Curtis & Co. was one of the largest importing houses in the nation and it remained prosperous until the 1860s. A series of disastrous investments by junior partner Joseph D. B. Curtis, however, eventually led to the collapse and dissolution of the firm. An 1869 balance sheet for the Paris house of L. & B. Curtis & Co. reveals that the firm had debts in excess of four million francs, of which 2,290,000 were uncollectable bad debts.
The documents on Moffat & Co. are particularly important. Moffat & Co., an "assaying and smelting associations," was a partnership formed in New York City in February 1849. The partners were John L. Moffat, president; Philo H. Perry, nephew of Joseph D. Beers, cashier; Joseph R. Curtiss (1813-); Samuel H. Ward (1814-1884); and Henry B. Conklin, all of New York City. Moffat & Co., in business from 1849 to 1851, was the largest and most reputable of all the private assaying, smelting, and coining firms established in California in the wake of the great gold rush. Folders 1055-1057 contain a copy of the articles of partnership, the agreement between Joseph D. Beers and Moffat & Co. by which Beers advanced $7,000 to the company, financial statements, and over thirty letters from Philo H. Perry to Beers telling of the activities of the firm and gold politics in California.
The New York and Mississippi Land Co., a joint stock company, was organized in 1835 for the purpose of buying and selling Chickasaw Indian lands in Mississippi. The company was capitalized at $150,000, 150 shares at $100 per share. J. D. Beers & Co. purchased 30 shares and Lewis & Benjamin Curtis 15 shares. Beers also invested in coal lands in the Scranton, Pennsylvania area. The files on Pennsylvania lands are found in folders 1062-1066. They contain a number of letters to and from Pennsylvania land agents Edward Dolph, C. W. Thompson, and Isaac J. Post. Joseph D. Beers also speculated in Michigan lands and came to own property in ten counties. Samuel Sherwood served as Beers' agent for these and other purchases.
Box 41 contains oversized material arranged in alphabetical order by person and subject. Most of the material is on business subjects, but there are also some personal files. See the folder listing for a listing of people and subjects. Boxes 42-45 contain twenty ledgers, memoranda books, notebooks, and checkbooks. Two memoranda books kept by Lewis Curtis, Box 42, have information about family and professional colleagues plus additional information on the collapse of L. & B. Curtis & Co. The rest of the material relates to the business activities of Joseph D. Beers, Lewis Curtis, Joseph D. B. Curtis and L. & B. Curtis & Co.
Series IV documents the personal lives and business careers of three generations of Beers, Curtises, and other relations through female lines. The most complete portraits are those for the families of Joseph D. Beers and Lewis Curtis. The series is particularly noteworthy for the material it includes on the entrepreneurial activities of Joseph D. Beers, Lewis Curtis, Joseph D. B. Curtis, and L. & B. Curtis & Co. Although the series contains material on family activities, the religious life of nineteenth century Americans, and the life of an American in Paris, it is primarily useful for its business papers. Researchers interested in such topics as the importing of dry goods; land speculation in Florida, Pennsylvania, Indiana, Illinois, and Michigan; Indian Reservation lands in New York; property in New York City, Brooklyn, and Jamaica, Long Island; speculation in Chickasaw lands; banking and state bonds; New Jersey railroads; or the smelting and minting of gold in California will all find this series rewarding.
Biographical / Historical
Lewis Perry Curtis was born in Southport, Connecticut on November 30, 1900. He graduated from Yale University (B.A., 1923; Ph.D. 1926) and joined the Yale faculty in 1927. Curtis was a prominent member of the faculty until 1969, teaching in the English and History Departments. He was instrumental in the establishment of the Division of History-Arts and Letters, and served as its director from 1956-1961. Curtis specialized in the study of eighteenth century British history and literature. He wrote many works on these topics. Curtis died in New Haven, Connecticut on April 8, 1976.
Business; Families; Land companies; United States -- Religion; New York (State); Account books; Deeds; Diaries; Beers, Joseph D.; Curtis, Benjamin Lewis, 1833-1900; Curtis, Lewis Agur, 1835-1909; Curtis, Lewis, 1787-1833; Beers family; Curtis family; Wells family
- L. P. Curtis Professional, 1912-1976; Series I; 5.4 linear feet (13 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I is divided into two sections, Correspondence and Other Papers. Correspondence contains all letters written to Lewis Perry Curtis by professional colleagues, students, and friends, plus a small number of his own papers. All correspondence is arranged alphabetically by surname of correspondent and then chronologically. Undated letters for each correspondent follow dated correspondence. Unidentified correspondence follows identified correspondence in Box 11, folders 351-356.
  As a general rule, there must be at least three letters by a correspondent for a separate listing, although there are some exceptions. Separate listings are occasionally given for relatives and important single letters by a correspondent. Normally, one or two letters from an individual are filed alphabetically with the first letter of the surname. The letter files, for example, A, D, and E, are found at the beginning of each letter. Anyone looking for the letters of a person must examine two series. Letters from friends and professional colleagues can be found in Series I and Series III and letters from relatives in Series II and III. Those interested in the correspondence of particular people should, in addition to examining the box and folder listing for each appropriate series, examine the relevant letter files, because it is possible for a person to be listed in one series but not be listed in a second.
  Other Papers primarily contains research materials for Lewis Perry Curtis. Following one folder of Yale materials, is a 1764 questionnaire sent out by the Archbishop of York, and fifteen folders of answers. The answers are arranged alphabetically by parish. The other major group of Archbishop of York Papers consists of photostats of letters. These are arranged in page number order.
  Correspondents who wrote ten or more letters are marked with an asterisk (*).
  Folders with asterisks (*) contain ten or more items.
  - Correspondence
    - A, 1933-1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Abbott, Louise(*), 1916-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Acheson, Dean Gooderham, 1944, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Acheson, Alice, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Allison, John M. S., 1923-1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Anderson, James R., 1942, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Anderson, Margeret, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Angell, James K., 1924-1925, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Armstrong, Heline, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Ashburn, Frank(*), 1944-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ashton, Leigh, 1954-1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Auchincloss, Reginald, 1943-1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Auden, George A.(*), 1923-1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Axtell, James L.(*), 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Aydelotte, William O, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Ba - Bh, 1930-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bi - Bu, 1917-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bahlman, Dudley W. R., 1957-1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Balderston, Katherine(*), 1925-1946 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Barhydt, Steele, 1939-1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Barringer, Allen C., 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bates, Robert Chapman(*), 1928-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
    - Beale, Howard Q. C., 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Bensly, Edward, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Blum, John M., 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Borden, Jane, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Bordley, James III(*), 1922-1970 (Box 1, Folder 27-31)
    - Bosanquet, Barbara, 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Bosanquet, Charles(*), 1932-1971 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Bowen, John G., 1950 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Bowles, Chester, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Bresson, Charlotte Clarke de(*), 1954, 1961-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Brewster, Kingman, 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Brody, Lawrence B., 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Browne, George, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Browne, Kenneth R. G.(*), 1923 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Buckley, William F. Jr., 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Ca, 1914-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Ch - C1, 1927-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Co - Cu, 1929-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Calleo, David P., 1957-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Cameron, David, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Cameron, Donald R., 1940, 1951, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Cameron, Olive(*), 1940-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Cannon, Beekman Cox(*), 1937-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 49-50)
    - Cannon, Margaret(*), 1947-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Carpenter, Philip, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Cash, Arthur H., 1965-1976 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Chapman, Frank(*), 1960-1975 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Chapman, R. V.(*), 1929-1937 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Chase, Daniel(*), 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Chase, Terry, 1959-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Cheng Yuan, 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Chrystie, Frances, 1929, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Coffin, Henry S., 1929 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Coles, Marvin J., 1940-1947 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Comiskey, Stephen A.(*), 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Connelly, Margaret, 1923-1924 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Cooper, George Brinton, 1943-1959 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Cooper, James Wayne, 1943-1976 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Cooper, Louise Field, 1951-1974 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Cooper, Mollie, 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Cooper, T. P.(*), 1926-1932 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Crocker, John, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Crosby, Sarah(*), 1946-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Cross, Wilbur L.(*), 1925-1933, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Curtis, Lewis Perry(1900-1976)(*), 1929-1973 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Curtis, Lewis Perry(1900-1976):bills, receipts, etc., 1931-1941 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Curtis, Lewis Perry(1900-1976): papers, 1931-1945, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Curtiss, Joseph Toy(*), 1924-1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 75-77)
    - Cushman, Charles, 1919-1920 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Cushman, Trevor, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Da - De, 1941-1974 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Di - Du, 1923-1970 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Danaher, John A., 1941 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - De Beers, Frederick S., Jr., 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Derby, John Barlow, 1924-1943 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Di Corcia, Joseph N., 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Dickson, S. Henry, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Dohan, David, 1940-1968 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Drake, Barbara, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Duemling, Robert W., 1950-1970 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Duff, R. S., 1955 undated (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Dunham, William Huse, Jr.(*), 1928-1974 (Box 3, Folder 91-92)
    - Dunn, John J., 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Dunster House Bookshop, Inc., 1927, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - E, 1929-1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Ebor, William, 1931-1936, undated (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Egerer, Joel W.(*), 1944-1975 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Ellis, George M., 1942-1946 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - d'Entreves, Comte Alessandro(*), 1958-1969 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Evelyn, William, 1923-1930 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - F, 1929-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Ferrell, Robert H., 1961, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Fife, John Priestly, 1921-1922, undated (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Fletcher, Sir Angus(*), 1949-1959, undated (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Flint, Margaret, 1945-1966 (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Foord, Archibald S., 1941-1968 (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Forley, Maurice, 1929-1970 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Fox, George R. Lane, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Fox, Seymour N., 1959 (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - France, George A., 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - French, Margaret, 1931-1964 (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - French, Robert Dudley(*), 1929-1953, undated (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Furniss, Edgar S., 1932-1965 (Box 4, Folder 113)